Guide to the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees International Union, Local 6 Photographs PHOTOS.098
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees International Union, Local 6 Photographs
1888-1980
1935-1975
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Hotel Employees & Restaurant Employees International Union. Local 6 (Hotel, Restaurant and Club Employees Union) (New York, N.Y.)
Ward, Peter
PHOTOS.098
2.75 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons, 1 oversize flat box, and 3 folders in an oversize shared box.
Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees International Union (HERE), Local 6 (now affiliated with the international union UNITE/HERE) represents housekeeping staff, waiters, bartenders and other categories of service employees in hotels, private clubs and restaurants in the New York City area. The local grew substantially as a result of a major organizing drive in the mid-1930s, under Local president Michael J. Obermeier. Significant gains came in 1938, with the signing of the first city-wide contract for hotel employees in many crafts and unions. The majority of this collection is comprised of photographs documenting the activities of HERE, Local 6. Topics include organizing campaigns and strikes, special events, workers and work sites and portraits of Local 6 leaders and members. Also included in this collection are over one hundred and fifty negatives (4 x 5 inches) which document Local 6 events between 1945 and 1950. Finally, there are three films from 1963 and a small number of artifacts, including a "Miss Union Maid" doll.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are opn without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated to the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives by the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees International Union, Local 6 in 1997, under an agreement with Peter Ward, President of the Council. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1950.196, NPA.2002.060, NPA.2002.016, NPA.2002.060, NPA.2003.049, and NPA.2005.230.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into four series. Series I, II and IV are arranged alphabetically, Series III is arranged chronologically.
Series I: General Files, 1888-1966
Series II: Editor's Files (Mildred Grossman), 1912-1980
Series III: Negatives, 1945-1950
Series IV: Other Materials, 1963-1977
Historical/Biographical Note
Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees International Union, Local 6 (now affiliated with the international union UNITE/HERE) represents housekeeping staff, waiters, bartenders and other categories of service employees in hotels, private clubs and restaurants in the New York City area. The local grew substantially as a result of a major organizing drive in the mid-1930s, under Local president Michael J. Obermeier, and absorbed a number of smaller locals of hotel employees over the years. Significant gains came in 1938, with the signing of the first city-wide contract for hotel employees in many crafts and unions; the contract was negotiated by the newly formed umbrella group of hotel unions, the New York City Hotel Trades Council (HTC), headed by Jay Rubin. The HTC has continued to negotiate with the united employers (organized in the New York Hotel Association) on behalf of many categories of hotel employees. The Local is ethnically diverse, and has always included a high proportion of Latino workers.
Related Archival Materials
Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees International Union, Local 6 Records (WAG 148)
New York Hotel and Motel Trades Council Records (WAG 123)
New York Hotel and Motel Trades Council Photographs (PHOTOS 097)
Scope and Content Note
The majority of this collection is comprised of photographs documenting the activities of HERE, Local 6. Topics include organizing campaigns and strikes, special events, workers and work sites and portraits of Local 6 leaders and members. Many of the photographs were taken by prominent labor photographer Mildred Grossman, who worked as a staff photographer for the New York Hotel Trades Council beginning in 1955. Also included in this collection are over one hundred and fifty negatives (4 x 5 inches) which document Local 6 events between 1945 and 1950. The negatives are accompanied by detailed caption and date information. Finally, there are three films from 1963 and a small number of artifacts, including a "Miss Union Maid" doll.
Hotels |x Employees |z New York (State) |z New York.; Artifacts (object genre); Photographs.; Strikes and lockouts -- New York (State) -- New York.; Hotels |z New York (State) |z New York.; Restaurants -- New York (State) -- New York; Bartenders.; Clippings (information artifacts); Buttons (information artifacts).; Restaurants |x Employees |x Labor unions |z United States.; Obermeier, Michael J., 1892-; Rubin, Jay; New York Hotel Trades Council; Grossman, Mildred, 1916-1988; Hotel Employees & Restaurant Employees International Union. Local 6 (Hotel, Restaurant and Club Employees Union) (New York, N.Y.); New York Hotel Association; Ward, Peter
- Series I: General Files, 1888-1966
  - Betty Bentz (I), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Betty Bentz (II), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Betty Bentz and Martin Luther King, Jr., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Business Cards], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Buttons and Emblems, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Certificates (Oversize), 1888, 1966 (Box Shared Tamiment OS009, Folder 1)
  - [Clippings], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clubs, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Constitutions and By-Laws, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - [Contact Sheets], undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - [Deframed Photographs], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hoh, Joseph: Campaign, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hotel Algonquin: Organizing, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - [Hotel Fact Sheet], undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - [Hotel Press Releases], 1964-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - [Graphics] (Oversize), undated (Box Shared Tamiment OS009, Folder 2)
  - Membership Party Faction, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - [Mounted Photographs], 1938, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Neighborhood Services Council (Baseball), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17A)
  - [Portraits], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - [Portraits] (Oversize I), 1941-1953 (Box Shared Tamiment OS009, Folder 3)
  - [Portraits] (Oversize II), undated (Box 4)
  - Souvenir Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Unidentified Meeting, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - [Unidentified Negatives], undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Series II: Editor's Files (Mildred Grossman), 1912-1980
  - Automat Strike, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bar, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Carpenters, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dining Room, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Elections, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Electricians, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Employment Office, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Front Service, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Gov. Clinton (Strike), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Health Center, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Hilton Rye (Tarrytown Strike), Jun 1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - History (Original Prints), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - [Hotel Trades Council Event], undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - [Hotel Trades Council Event] (I), undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - [Hotel Trades Council Event] (II), undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - [Hotel Trades Council Event] (III), undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - [Hotel Trades Council Event] (IV), undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Hotel Workers, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Housekeeping, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Illustrations, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Insurance and Hospitality, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Kitchen, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Labor History, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - [Lane, Gertrude: Funeral], undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Lexington Strike, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Local 6 History, 1941-1948 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Maintenance, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - McAlpin Picket, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous (I), undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous (II), 1937 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous (III), 1938 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous (IV), 1940 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Mistakes, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - [Mounted Photographs], undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Negatives, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Parties, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Post 1939 (1), undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Post 1939 (II), undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Rubin, Jay, 1937, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Signing Photos, 1939-1945; undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - [Sol Abramson], undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - [Strikers], 1912, 1913, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Strikers, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Strikers, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Strikers, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Telephone [Operator], undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Then and Now (I), undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Then and Now (II), undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Union Activity, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Waldorf Strike, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Photo Lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Series III: Negatives, 1945-1950
  - Waldorf Mechanics, Meetings, Mar 9, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hotel and Insurance Meeting, Mar 19, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Local 1, Payment of Insurance Checks to Widows, Apr 2, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - HTC Waldorf Workers Meeting, Jun 18, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Waldorf Election, Jul 27, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Walfdorf Election - Toasting, Jul 27, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Obermeier-Lopez, Lane and Waldorf Commission, Aug 7, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Treasury Award for Bond Sale, Sep 7, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bill Randolf, Leaflet Distribution, Oct 19, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Lexington Election Victory Group, Oct 2, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Waldorf Election Vote Counting, Dec 18, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Victory Celebration of Waldorf Workers, Dec 18, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - HTC Signing Contract with Hotel Association, Dec 19, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Osato and Pickets in Front of Spanish Consulate, Mar 2, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - HTC Donating Truckload of Food to Westinghouse Strikers in Bloomfield and Elizabeth, NJ Locals, Mar 18, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Signing Waldord Contract Commissioner Mullrooney's Office, Mar 27, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Hotel Wellington, Interracial Solidarity of Workers, Jul 29, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Anniversary Banquet for Local 6 Chefs, Jan 31, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Anti-Racial Discrimination Meeting, Feb 15, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Welcoming Back of Mike Obermeier, Mar 4, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Anti-Discrimination Commission, Mar 4, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Imperial Hotel Group Signing Petition for New Jobs, Mar 12, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - HTC Executive Board Meeting, Mar 13, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - New York Visit of Fruit Service Employees, Apr 11, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Jay Rubin's Address and Conference Vote (Park Central), May 8, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Team and Baby Birthday Party, Jul 26, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Laundry at Astor, Aug 11, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Club Workers Meeting at Park Central Hotel, Aug 12, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - HTC Fighting Defense Fund, Sep 2, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Lois Manchead Collecting for Defence Fund, Oct 7, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Mike Obermeier Hearing, Nov 1, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Biennial Convention of Local 6 (Park Central Hotel), Nov 8, 1947 - Nov 9, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Election at Palm Gardens, Nov 12, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Biennial Convention (Park Central), Dec 11, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Meeting in Banquet Department, Contributing to the Obermeier Defence Fund, Dec 15, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Murroney Receiving Check from Angelo for Obermeier Defence Fund, Jan 19, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Election Day (Belmont Plaza, St. George Manhattan Center), Jan 28, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Party at Headquarters for the Footlighters, Feb 13, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Mike Obermeier, Pickets, Mar 3, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Howard Rohr, Mike Obermeier Defence Fund Contribution (Hotel Pierre), Mar 4, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Wallace Meeting (Marc and Judge Rainey), Apr 12, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Insurance Plan Operations, Apr 26, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Mike Obermeier Plaque and Guest Emblem, May 11, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Mike Obermeier Testimonial Dinner (Astor), May 20, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Committee for Food for Striking Miners, Mar 1, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - HTC, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Bill Randolf, Waldorf Election Victory Meeting, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Local 1 Office Staff and Charter of 1910, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Membership Rally (St Nicholas Arena), undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Series IV: Other Materials, 1963-1977
  - [Decorative Centerpieces], 1977 (Box 5)
  - Doll: "Miss Union Maid", undated (Box 5)
  - Paperweight: "N.Y.C. Central Labor Council Executive Board", Mar 20, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Reel: 25th Anniversary Dinner (Cutaways), Feb 21, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Reel: 25th Anniversary Dinner (Work Print), Feb 21, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Reel: Puerto Rican Day Parade (Hyde Park Trip), May 20, 1963 (Box 3)